<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lues venera wherein the names, nature, subject, causes, signes, and cure, are handled, mistakes in these discovered, rectified, doubts and questions succinctly resolved / by John Wynell ...</title>
            <author>Wynell, John, fl. 1660-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12269722</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12269722</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58193</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67222)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58193)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1516:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lues venera wherein the names, nature, subject, causes, signes, and cure, are handled, mistakes in these discovered, rectified, doubts and questions succinctly resolved / by John Wynell ...</title>
                  <author>Wynell, John, fl. 1660-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 76, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.W. for the author and are to be sold by H. Herringman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sexually transmitted diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Syphilis --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Gonorrhea --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58193:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LUES <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ENEREA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN The Names, Nature, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, Cauſes, Signes, and Cure, are Handled.</p>
            <p>Miſtakes in theſe diſcovered Rectified; Doubts and Queſtions Succinctly Reſolved.</p>
            <p>BY JOHN WYNELL. <hi>M.D.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Deſidia &amp; Luxuria, haec duo priùs in Graecia corpora vitiârunt, deinde apud nos afflixerunt— <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>um reclè cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum eſſe dicunt, quem prima origo cauſae non fefellerir— Alii putant intereſſe, non quid morbum faciat, ſed quid tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. <bibl>
                  <hi>Celſus.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W.W.</hi> for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>H. Herringman,</hi> in the lower Walk in the new Exchange. 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58193:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58193:2"/>
            <head>To my deſervedly honoured Friend, <hi>James Boevey,</hi> of <hi>Upper-Chelſey,</hi> Eſq;.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the Sanction of long-liv'd Cuſtom, that no one appear to publick view, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Dedication to ſome conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Friend. And while others affect to chuſe Nobles by Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and mutable Titles; I, one Noble by Nature, and a better portion of her endowments, the moſt primary, true and immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dignity; which is not, <hi>in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norante,</hi> nor in the power of Men or Laws, to give or take away; but immures it ſelf in your Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
<pb facs="tcp:58193:3"/>and ſheds its beams of love and favour on all ingenious men (known) of what faculty ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. Sir, Bountifull Nature (to give an inſtance of what ſhe can do) hath beſtow'd on you (not laviſh'd) much more than a child's part, (the leſſe ſhe hath for ſome others, for her ſtore is not infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.) I write not this to make you known, whom all <hi>Europe</hi> knows already: Much leſſe would I offer dirty Wits an occaſion to ſlurre you, by this Dedication, as if the Argument enſuing ſpake your diſeaſe, and therefore fitteſt for your view, ſtudy, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. No, Eagles are not wont to prey on carrion. Great minds, ſublime fancies, (furniſhed with
<pb facs="tcp:58193:3"/>Arts, Tongues, enriched with the advantages of Travell, kept in buſieſt ſpeculative employments) I ſay, Great Souls, (whoſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity the locall world is too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to circumſcribe) are above theſe carnall ineſcations, &amp; leave them condemn'd to thoſe, whoſe ſouls dwell in their ſenſes. This Treatiſe hath lien in broken pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſome years paſt, (penned for private uſe) and had never ſeen more light, but by your encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement. And now, being got abroad, firſt offers ſelf to you, to pay its birth duty and reſpects for publick freedom. It lies in a ſmall bulk, and without Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall ornament, for, it intends the diſeaſed, to make them known
<pb facs="tcp:58193:4"/>to themſelves; appales to abide the narrow ſcan of your curious fancy, which knows neither bonds nor reſt, (the more's your danger.) For, let me tell you, Sir, you have a mind, (whom to ſupply with neceſſary animal-ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits) is able to depauperate the moſt juſt and equilibrious Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. And provident Nature will ſtore her Head-quarters, and not fail to ſend enough to her Court and Univerſity, though the lower Towns and Villages of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſm fail and pine for it. For the animal ſpirits luminous and aetherial, (fit to irradiate the ſoul's commands through the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perforate Nerves) are raiſed out of the Vitall (in the <hi>Plexus Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roides</hi>)
<pb facs="tcp:58193:4"/>by further elaboration; whence Nature amaunds the more foeculent part to the ſewers of the Brain, and the reſidue by the veines to the Heart, for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concoction. Hence, the weak and depopulate bodies of buſieſt minds. Hence, thoſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome floods of rheums and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillations in them, whoſe nature delights to dwell largely in the Animals, (eſpecially, <hi>quibus natura mater, fortuna noverca.</hi>) And ſuch would be your condition, did not Fortune and Prudence conſpire, to prompt you a more elegant and defoecated diet to prevent it. But what do I, ſetting up my Candle to your Torch, caſting my Mite of advice into the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury
<pb facs="tcp:58193:5"/>of your prudentiall Rules? Your Tongue and Pen drop little elſe, and your loving Soul can do no leſſe, than to publiſh and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the ſtock of Learning, with your methodicall Digeſts.</p>
            <p>All the divertiſement that I ſhall further give your ſerious em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, is, to ſignifie and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, that I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your affectionate Servant, <hi>JOHN WYNELL.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Dureſm-Yard</hi> 
                  <date>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>Nonas Decemb.</hi> 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58193:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEfore thou enter the Treatiſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, peruſe well this Epiſtle directed unto thee; wherein thou haſt, <hi>1</hi> The <hi>Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> that induced the penning and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of it. <hi>2</hi> My <hi>Scope,</hi> or End therein. <hi>3</hi> The <hi>advanragious Uſe</hi> that thou maist make thereof.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> The <hi>Occaſion</hi> was made up of theſe <hi>Obſervations</hi> following. <hi>1</hi> Of the stupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious <hi>grouth</hi> and <hi>ſpreading</hi> of two depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating diſeaſes, the <hi>Venercous,</hi> and the <hi>Scurvy:</hi> And (enquiring thereupon into their effects, in the yearly Bills of Mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) I found them ſo benign, that it gave me occaſion to admire the mystery of conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I obſerved the <hi>Conſumption</hi> (in this ſulphury aire) to have ſlain its thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands; and the <hi>Venereous diſeaſe</hi> ſcarce its hundreds. I concluded thereupon, that,
<pb facs="tcp:58193:6"/>
               <hi>Latet dolus in generalibus,</hi> Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on's back is broad enough to bear ſuch mocks. I perceived alſo, that the <hi>Scurvy</hi> had ſcarce a conſtant name in the killing Catalogue, (though it deſtroy more than any ten of its fellowes) but the <hi>Dropſie, Feavours</hi> of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kinds, &amp;c. have great numbers dead at their feet. I concluded thence, that, <hi>Filiae devorârunt matrem. 2,</hi> I obſerved the <hi>mortality and pining of great, noble, and generous Families,</hi> their generations gaſping, and ſoon run out, one treading on the heels of another, which gave me to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what ſhould be the occaſion. And guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my thoughts by that rule, <hi>Cauſa &amp; Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus ſunt ſimul;</hi> I accuſed their pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering diet, effeminate education, praema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture marriage, indiſcreet covetouſneſſe, in taking a weak, crooked, rickety woman, (for her Portion) to be <hi>mater familiâs.</hi> But my thoughts (reaſoning against the ſufficiency of this enumeration, as not of ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration) carried me with greateſt reaſon to their diſeaſes. And finding the Venereous diſeaſe amongſt them, (as in its head-quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) I was ſtrong in my conjecture, that
<pb facs="tcp:58193:6"/>this (traduced in the ſeed of parents, and mi1k of nurſes, hindring nature in accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing her intention of perfection) hath brought this calamity on great Families, <hi>Haeret ſemini lethalis arundo. 3,</hi> I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved further, that hereby, one principall end of Marriage, (to propagate a ſtrong, healthy, and numerous poſterity, fit to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the being, name, and memory of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, to ſuch an eternity, as their mortall condition is capable of) was much made void. For (in this wanton, painting, patching, perfuming Iſſuing age) a man knows not whom or what he, takes, to himſelf or his ſon, in marriage, a bleſſing, or a curſe. Whereby not onely our own bodies are endangered, damnified; but poſterity, primarily, founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, corrupted, extirpated; hearts of yoke-fellowes alienated, iealouſie let in (of non-faithfulnſſe after, having loſt their girdle before:) and indeed, an uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life together, becauſe they cannot aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, (like two dogs in a chain, ever ſnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) and all becauſe abuſefull deceit in the marriage, <hi>Manet altâ mente repô<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum.</hi> And now, no ſecuring evidence from
<pb facs="tcp:58193:7"/>the <hi>Hymen</hi> (as amongſt the Jews antiently) being found; Nature now in formation, rarely plating any ſuch tranſverſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brane; the weeping breach whereof may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the husband, he is not deceived in his choice. <hi>4.</hi> I obſerved alſo, that all preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Phyſick, gave out a more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary skill in the Venereous Cure; yet, ſcarce one patient of ten went off from them ſound, (as by relapſe it too ordinarily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears.) I was therefore led to believe, that either the ignorance of the diſeaſe, or ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'dneſſe to diſcover it, made them carry it about them too long; or the ignorance of ſuch as they applyed unto, or the impatience of Patients to bear a cure, gave the diſeaſe this advantage. For, though by palliation, the dolorous ſymptoms w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re baffled; yet, the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulent cauſe was left in the dark, (deep in their ſpirits and bones, and made future work for the Phyſitian. Hereby their Patients are deceived, who (not being able to judge) think better of their recovery than is meet and ſafe; and find by ſad experience, that (the next evoking ſeaſon) the diſeaſe (get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſtrength, by lying in trenches) breaks
<pb facs="tcp:58193:7"/>forth more dangerouſly, than was its firſt onſet.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> My <hi>ſcope</hi> therefore in publiſhing this little Treatiſe, is, to preſent a good office to my Nation, by entring the lists with this Champion; who (by trampling on ſuch eminent members of it) abates its grandure, and bids defiance to all the boast of Remedies in the Common-wealth of Phyſick. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſince <hi>publicos in hoſtes quilibet homo miles;</hi> I ſent out my Scouts, that I might acquaint my ſelfe with the enemy in all his motions. I enquired after an, Army that would not run, untill they had broken his pride. I conſidered, how I might cut off proviſions, ſupplies, r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cruits; and finally, how I might engage the Enemie's whole body, untill I had cleared him of all the coasis and quarters of the Microcoſm. Whereby I conceived, I ſhould deſerve well of my ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Country-men; by, not. ſuffering the grandure of the Nation to lie trodden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the foot of a proud stranger, and I ſtand by as an idle ſpectator. And ſince this Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my plaies ſmall game alſo, and is come down ſo low as on the Spinſter; I have therefore
<pb facs="tcp:58193:8"/>made him ſpeak plain engliſh, (not without due reſpect to modeſty, and better underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings) that ordinary capacities may be able to judge of their owne condition by their owne light; and in ſeaſon look out for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, before captivity, and the further ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of a valiant Nation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>advantagious uſe</hi> of theſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, either reſpects all, that, having been in unknown Hypocauſts, have any reaſon, from peruſing this Treatiſe, to ſuſpect their bodily condition) to deal prudently for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by ſeeking reliefe in ſeaſon. Or eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, ſuch as intend marriage, and the bleſſings of it; that they get them bodies made fit for marriage. For though they know their owne perſonall integrity, yet what lurks in their humors from parent's ſeed, or nurſes milk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, they are ignorant of. And, however no preſent ſymptoms thereof diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it to themſelves, much leſſe to others; yet the <hi>fomes</hi> of it, (oft and long lying ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure) doth traduce a preſent defilement in generation to poſterity. And (by marriage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duty) that latent diſpoſition is urged to break forth the ſooner, (and will without
<pb facs="tcp:58193:8"/>ſuch ſtimulation make it ſelf known in time.) And though the purſuance of this Advice may queſtion their Honour, yet it provides for their owne, and poſteritie's ſafety, which all wiſe men highly value.</p>
            <p>I have read many Authors on this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and found ſatisfaction in none, (or this Treatiſe had been ſilenc'd.) I perceive, that on this (as on other Subjects) they too much tread in the steps of their Anceſtors, and reſt in their dictates without further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry; (ſwelling their volumes with tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions into their owne methods) which ſerves to fill Libraries with much paper, yet few Bòcks. But every man's breath will ſmell ſomewhat of his diet, and after-ages can but <hi>inventis addere;</hi> which hath been my endeavour throughout. And though I write in Engliſh, that all may know their condition of body, (as is fit) yet have I not ſet bogglers at work on the Therapeutick part, of which they are uncapable. If in this ſervice I am accepted; then maiſt thou, ere long, expect another Treatiſe, <hi>Of the Scurvy,</hi> (if an abler Pen (which were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:58193:9"/>acceptable) or want of leiſure prevent m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not.) Wherein the Preſſe hath failed, thou maiſt excuſe: but wherein I have erred, or come ſhort, (if the more learned ſhall can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly correct or ſupply) it (tending to the advancement of health, and of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Learning) ſhall be friendly taken by,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine health-Servant,</hi> J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58193:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LUES VENEREA.</hi> Wherein its Names, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Subject, Cauſes, Signs, and Cure, are handled. The miſtakes in theſe, diſcover'd, rectified; and many Doubts and Queſtions, ſuccinctly reſolved.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Praeface.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat <hi>Africk</hi> is never without ſome new <hi>Monſter,</hi> nor <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> without ſome new <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> as ſtrange &amp; mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous, is a truth that needs no proof. But the proper reaſons hereof are hard to find, and doe leſſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58193:10"/>appeare. Some ſend as far as the Starrs, and accuſe the inclemency of their influences; Others go no farther then the Kitchen, and accuſe our diet of too much variety and change from the plaineneſſe of the Antient healthier times, &amp; our new inventions of Sperm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firing Cookery. But a Chriſtian looks yet higher, to the diſpleaſure of God, at the new and horrid ſins of man acted by the body, chaſtiſed and marked out by new and unheard-of diſeaſes, of which this is one.</p>
               <p>Before the yeare 1493. this diſeaſe never gave a viſit to <hi>Europe,</hi> kept its own region in the then unknown Weſtern world, where it was Endemical. Thence (as 'tis ſtoried) the followers of <hi>Chr. Columbus</hi> returning brought it, and gave it to the <hi>Ital<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an</hi> women, and they to the <hi>French</hi> Souldiers at the ſiege of <hi>Naples, Sua ſimul pudenda et pudendum morbum communicàrunt.</hi> After that ſiege, the <hi>French</hi> returning, brought it to thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat were or ſhould be their wives from whom they received a malevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58193:10"/>benevolence. And when it was come ſo near us, we (that delight to imitate the <hi>French</hi>) tooke their faults and their faſhions together. And this diſeaſe (liking this fertile Soyle) amongſt us brought forth a dreadfull encreaſe. <hi>Braſſavolus</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved long ſince 234 ſeverall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences (accidental he meanes); and, amongſt us, ſcarce in two ſeverall bodies hath it the ſame face and phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noms, ſo ſtrangely, (in the effects and ſymptoms) did it ſoon appear, and therein the wrath of God. And that this is to be looked on as the moſt conſiderable cauſe of its grouth in <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> and plentifull ſpreading amongſt us, we ſhall eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that (when firſt this Peſt began to break out there, and became more ſpreading of late here) the wickedneſſe of man encreaſed. Great warrs, and of long continuance, were moved by mighty Nimrods, heat
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58193:11"/>of blood, brought forth heat of luſt, the inſatiability whereof was puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by this new Peſt.</p>
               <p>But not to ſtay the reader on the provoking cauſe (or the avenging hand) I ſhall next lead him to the beſt Definition of this diſeaſe that I can finde, that it may appear by its Eſſence, after I have given it its name.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Names.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WEE commonly (knowing whence we had it) call it the <hi>French Pox.</hi> They for the ſame reaſon (for none take pleaſure to owne it) intitle it the <hi>Neapolitan, Italian,</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh.</hi> They again whip the vagarant, give it a paſſe-port and ſend it to the place of its birth, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it the <hi>Indian</hi> diſeaſe. Some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, (obſerving how ill it is taken by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58193:11"/>each Nation, (that it ſhould take the name of its Sire from their Country) have found or made a name for it, (from its firſt quarters commonly) and will have it called <hi>Pudendagra.</hi> But (what word bearing no modeſt Engliſh Tranſlation) we, without ſlurring any other Nation, as making them reputed fathers of the common Baſtard, (and knowing our ſelves) do chooſe rather to call it the <hi>Venereous diſeaſe;</hi> or, (in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiſtinction to the <hi>Variolae</hi>) the <hi>Grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And there is no leſſe diſſent and claſhing, amongſt Authors of the firſt note, in defining its nature, than in aſſigning its name; which comes to paſſe, by the deep ſilence and darkneſs of the Antients, in that they had no light from the Fathers of Phyſick, to ſlay and be a <hi>Baſis</hi> to their thoughts. And therefore I ſhall take my liberty alſo, and give you its nature and beeing, thus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58193:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Definition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Venereous diſeaſe is, <hi>A praeternaturall Affect or Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man's body, primarily, and of it ſelf, hurting or offending the Naturall Operations (and thence the Vital and Animal) from a cauſe or reaſon occult or unknown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I call it an <hi>Affect</hi> or <hi>Diſpoſition,</hi> not in a ſtrict ſenſe, as oppoſed to Habit, (as if I thought it eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved) but in a large and genrall ſenſe, ſuch as may imply Habit as well as Diſpoſition. For this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe in weaker and more depravable conſtitutions, becomes ſo rooted, and hath committed ſuch waſte in the Vital and Animal ſpirits, and induced ſuch an Atony on the whole Microcoſm, as may admit Palliation, but not Cure. I call it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58193:12"/>
                  <hi>Praeternaturall,</hi> in oppoſition to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, ordinate, and preſerving diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. And, <hi>Of man's body;</hi> for there is no diſeaſe of man's body, (this excepted) but is common to them with beaſts; but this befalls mankind onely, (more luſtfully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiate than the beaſts themſelves). I ſay farther, That it <hi>hurts and offends the naturall operations;</hi> it being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſuch as labour under this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, that ſome naturall operation be offended. And I call them <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> (retaining the old received di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction) in oppoſition to Vital and Animal, as ariſing from the Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble faculty, (which the <hi>Stoicks</hi> called <hi>Nature</hi>) amongſt whom, Nutrition, Augmentation, and Generation, are contained, and ſuch other ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations as ariſe from, and are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to them. Now, there is a three-fold hurt or offence done to any operation, <hi>viz.</hi> Abolition, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution, and Depravation. And,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58193:13"/>in this diſeaſe, the operations are evidently depraved: I do not ſay, they are not diminiſhed, but they are alwaies depraved; and as far as they are diminiſhed, it comes on them by depravation. Then I ſay, <hi>Primarily, and of it ſelf;</hi> becauſe, though the Vital and Animal ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations be alſo (and ſpeedily) offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; yet it is Secondarily, and by reaſon that the naturall operations were firſt offended; and ſo, not as Animals and Vitals, but as Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral bodies, have they their firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury. Laſtly, I ſay, <hi>For,</hi> or <hi>from a cauſe or reaſon, occult and unknown.</hi> To diſtinguiſh this from other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, concerning whom, it appears, whence, how, and when, the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations are iujured, either by diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, or corruption, or ſome other manifeſt way. But, how this diſeaſe wounds the operations, is very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, and we hardly find words to expreſſe, what we conceive of it.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58193:13"/>And though in the diſeaſe, ulcers, and gummy tumors do appear, and other loathſome ſymptoms, (as in the Chapter of Signs more at large); yet theſe are not the diſeaſe it ſelf, much leſſe the cauſes, but the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. I deny not, that the effects do appear, and oft do, where the true nature, reaſon, and cauſes thereof, lie in the dark. If I ſhould call theſe ulcers and tumors, the diſeaſe, by a Metonymy; yet even in them is found, that which reaſon but imperfectly, much leſſe ſenſe, can know: For we do not find them cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by ſuch remedies, as give the effect by their firſt or manifeſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, or by any remedies, taught by the Antients; but by other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, and ſuch as are new, and were unknown unto them. Neither let this ſeem ſtrange, to affirm, that there are diſeaſes, whoſe nature, cauſe, and formall reaſons, lye ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure; for the evidence of this is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58193:14"/>prepared, and plainly made out to our hands, by learned <hi>Fernelius, De abditis rerum cauſts,</hi> from the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Antients. And thus much for the deſcription of the <hi>Diſeaſe Venereal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any object, that I have penned a Treatiſe, to make a diſeaſe better known to my Countrymen, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring under it, or in danger of it; and that I do in the iſſue reſolve all, <hi>in rationes incognitas,</hi> occult operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are <hi>ignorantiae aſyla.</hi> I anſwer, That of many things we know the <hi>quod ſit,</hi> not the <hi>cur ſit.</hi> When the Objectors can give me the reaſon of the ſtrength of the Neather-jaw; of the Load-ſtone's work and impotency; of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, its variation and ſtupor; of the motion of the Sea and Winds; of the production of the Stone and Worms; of the forms, and their tranſmuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in bodies mixt; of the cauſes and reaſons of operations in peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58193:14"/>diſeaſes; By that time, I ſhall further ſatisfie them. <hi>Qui nil dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, nil didicit: &amp; maxima pars eorum quae ſcimus, eſt minima pars eorum quae neſcimus.</hi> Shall the learned'ſt Lights of the Apollinaean Art, (called to ſet forth the cauſes and reaſons, of the Stone and Worms, in the ſeverall parts, ventricles, and cavities of the body; and being urged by ſtreſſe of argument) fly (to defend their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions) to <hi>Spiritus lapideſcens &amp; lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brificans,</hi> as the Eſſicient cauſe; and <hi>Materia lapideſcibilis &amp; lumbriſica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis,</hi> as the Materiall? Shall thoſe <hi>Heroes</hi> (in ſhewing the reaſon of peſtilent and malignant cacoethicall diſeaſes) fly to a cauſe, <hi>quae agit tota ſubſtantia,</hi> the <hi>Aſylum ignorantiae?</hi> Then, what excuſe or plea could my ignorance and madneſſe have, if in ſo learned an age, I ſhould tell the world in print, that I knew any thing ſo comprehenſively, as that I were ignorant of it in nothing;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58193:15"/>Whereas, there are more depths of nature in a little Gnat, then the learning of the World ſhall ever attain in this mortall ſtate. And he hath gone far in knowledge, that knowes his owne ignorance; And hee's unworthy to know more, that is aſhamed to conſeſſe it. And ſo much, by digreſſion. From the Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, I ſhall come to the Subject of this diſeaſe, and then more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly to the Effect it ſelf; which, (though they have been touched in the Definition,) yet being moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable parts, require a particular hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> The Subject of the Venereous Diſeaſe.</head>
               <p>AND that I take to be the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors (and ſpirits) primarily,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58193:15"/>and (by their circulation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſing themſelves throughout the body) there is no part ſecure from being, ſecondarily, the ſeat and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of it. Why the whole body is not alwayes afflicted of this diſeaſe, but the Members of generation, the mouth, and inſtruments of ſenſe and motion; no greater reaſon can be given, then the tenderneſſe of thoſe parts, their impotency to reſiſt ſuch an enemy, and their exquiſite ſenſe. That the humors firſt, and next the ſpirits, are the chief ſeat, this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to a reaſon undeniable; that the diſeaſe ſo ſpeedily ſpreads the whole body. Beſides, the ſpirits ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their chief reſidence in thoſe parts, (the genitalls, and ſeminary veſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls for generation,) the Liver, (according to old opinion) and the Veines, heart and maſſe of blood, (according to the new) and in the head for ſenſe and motion; theſe parts muſt needs be firſt, and more
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58193:16"/>taken of this diſeaſe, then the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, which with their nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment muſt of neceſſity, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſucceſſively have this defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conveyed unto them alſo. Neither may any one think, that the humors and ſpirits are no living bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and therefore, not the ſubject of this diſeaſe; Though I could grant the conſequence, yet the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent can never be made good. For can they be the firſt receivers, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and conveyers of Life unto the other parts, and yet have no life in themſelves? Are they nouriſhed, augmented, diminiſhed, (which are properties of living bodies) and yet be no living bodies? We conclude then, the humors and ſpirits to be the ſubjects of this diſeaſe; For they have the requiſite conditions of a true ſubject, which are theſe: That primarily, and of themſelves, and not by the intervention of any other, and alwayes, while the diſeaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58193:16"/>in the body, it is ſeated in them, though not alwayes in them onely. The truth of this opinion, you will the more reſt in, and with the greater evidence; if I avoid the pretended claime, that other parts of the body are ſuppoſed to have, to be the ſeats of this diſeaſe. There be three options only, amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, which are worthy to be taken into this conteſt.</p>
               <p>For ſome have ſeated this diſeaſe in them members of generation; others in the Liver<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a third ſort in the Head. Firſt, R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſon and experience both, will diſcharge the Genitalls, from being the ſubject of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. Reaſon, For then there were no ſuch diſeaſe in the body, but of neceſſity they muſt be offended, and injured: but we often find men ſtrongly taken of this diſeaſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ulcer, Tumor, or any other ſigne of wrong to the proper actions of thoſe parts. Beſides, if they were
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58193:17"/>the ſubject, and the diſeaſes lodged in them, then (ſuppoſing them to be amputed) the diſeaſe were cured, and the body rendred uncapable of it, (which cannot be granted.) For many receive this diſeaſe by inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, in the ſeed of their parents, one or both; and give it to their Nurſes. Many receive it from the venereous milk of their nurſes; the genitalls of both which, for a long while remain ſound. So that the members of generation are diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
               <p>Next to quit the Liver's claim, to be the ſeat of this diſeaſe, (which hath been the opinion of many Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians of note) againſt whom, I ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue thus. That part which is <hi>primò,</hi> and <hi>per ſe</hi> offended, is the ſubject of that offence, or diſeaſe injuring; but that's not the Liver: for Ulcers and Tumors ariſe in the genitalls, from this diſeaſe, (and that ſometimes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpeedily) which if by ſeaſonable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58193:17"/>and fit remedies they were Cured, the Liver and whole body would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſound. If any doubt, whether theſe Ulcers and Tumors be effects, and do ſhew the preſence of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe; let them enquire, How their bodies were contaminated, and by what Contact; alſo by what ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall remedies they were cured, and they will ceaſe to doubt. If then theſe effects diſcover the diſeaſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, then that diſeaſe (being an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident) muſt have a ſubject proper to it, which, we have proved the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitalls themſelves, (though offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) cannot be; much leſſe the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which for a time remains un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touch't, (the diſeaſe being as yet not propagated ſo farre.) There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, either the accident muſt be without a ſubject, or there is ſome other; for the Liver muſt ceaſe its claime. Beſides, it is well known, that the diſeaſe is propagated by Contact, and contact is not of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58193:18"/>Liver, which is far diſtant. Now, if the diſeaſe enter the body by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tact, it is then immediately, in its proper ſubject, or not; If not, then the diſeaſe paſſeth from ſubject to ſubject, and ſo hath no proper ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Further, If the Liver were the proper ſubject, then (to ſpeak in their language) the ſanguifying fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty muſt neceſſarily be preſently vitiated, as ſoon as the diſeaſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. For, if a bowell be vitiated, its proper faculty and work muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be forthwith vitiated. <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> will tell you, that where ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guification is vitiated, <hi>Fiunt fluxus ſanguinei, aut vitiatus color.</hi> The body nouriſhed by virulent blood, the whole habit of it becomes virulent. For, as is the blood, ſo is the fleſh, and conſequently the colour of the ſame, throughout the whole body. But that dark, ſqualid, fuſcous, dull, flowerleſſe colour, that uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompanieth and diſcovereth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58193:18"/>this diſeaſe (grown,) appeareth not of a long time, in many infected, in whom the diſeaſe lurks, as curbed and corrected by ſtronger ſpirits and bowells; and is in its progreſs reſiſted, (Nature endeavouring her own prefervation, and to keep her quarters ſecure.)</p>
               <p>Now for the third opinion, of thoſe that make the Head the ſeat and ſubject of this diſeaſe. If not the Liver or Genitals, much leſſe the Head can be: for many have the diſeaſe grown (as appears by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting-ſymptoms;) and yet find no ſenſible injury thereby, in their heads. Again, The Head is never primarily and immediately affected, but becauſe ſome other parts of the body have been firſt taken with this diſeaſe; and, therefore, not the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Beſides, the effects of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe have often been removed from the Head, and yet this Peſt remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in other parts of the body, (which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58193:19"/>ſufficiently evinceth the opinion aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, and confuteth the contrary.) Now, though grievous ſymptoms, as flames, puſtules, hard tumors, ringing in the ears, dimneſſe of ſight, falling away of the hair; and many other effects of this diſeaſe appear in the head: Yet theſe are cauſed by the contagion, carried along in the humours and vitall ſpirits, which are diſtributed through the whole body; who (eſpecially moving towards the head, and having this diſeaſe lodged in them) produce theſe effects there. For the ſpirits being light ſubſtances, thin, and paſſable, do naturally move upwards, and, by their tenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, do pierce and paſſe through all the parts of the head; yet, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe hath not its ſeat there, (for the reaſon in the former Section deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered): For the proper and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall operations of the animal fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, are not offended by it, as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58193:19"/>Imagination, Reaſon, Memory. And if the ſenſory parts be offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, vitiated, and weakened by the diſeaſe, it is rather, by reaſon that they are naturall bodies, (nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by ſuch blood and ſpirits) than that they are the inſtruments of, and belonging to, the animal and rational faculty. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conclude, Not the Genitals, not the Liver, not the Head, but the Humours and Spirits, are the true and proper ſubjects of this diſeaſe; of which, I had not ſo much enlarged, but for that it is importantly neceſſary to be known, to direct, how the Cure is to be ſpecified and determined.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58193:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> What the Affect is, which is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Humours, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>IF you enquire what that Affect is, which is ſeated in the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and Spirits, I ſay, it is no other than a diſtemper. If, What diſtemper? a hot, cold, moiſt, or dry? I ſay, it may accompany any one, every one of them, and yet be another thing different from them. For the character of this diſeaſe is a certain degree and manner of diſtemper, which we have not words to expreſſe. Neither there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt we flye to a fourth kind or ſpecies of diſeaſes, (amongſt whom, to place this) to the Antients unknown, who have left us the acknowledgment but of three kinds, (though they knew a kind of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58193:20"/>that offend after a ſecret man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) for they knew the biting of a mad Dog, of which they could give no ſufficient reaſon, and yet they did not conſtitute another kind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the three, uſually received; for <hi>Modus aut gradus non variat ſpeciem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there is in this Diſeaſe a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and manner of diſtemper, above that which is Elementary, appears in this; that there are certain effects and impreſſions of it, that cannot be reduced to any manifeſt Diſtemper. The operations ariſe from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and they are injured or offended by Diſtemper. As therefore, perfect operations proceed from a like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Temper; ſo alſo, operations eminently offended, are thus offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a like degree of Diſtemper. Alſo we find, that this Diſeaſe is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by remedies, that do not cure manifeſt Diſtempers: yet, if they reſtore the operations, it is neceſſary, that they reſtore the Temper. But
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58193:21"/>ſeeing they do not, (as curing this Diſeaſe) reſtore the manifeſt Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; it followes, that they reſtore a degree of Temper, that we cannot expreſſe; and that they take away a like degree of Diſtemper, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>induced by this Diſeaſe. This alſo is to be conſidered; that this Diſeaſe may lodge in every Diſtemper: for in practice we find, that men of cold Diſtemper, as well as hot, and ſome of dry, and maraſmodicall bodies, as well as the moiſt, and ſucculent, are taken with this Diſeaſe. So that this Diſtemper may joyne with any, with every Diſtemper. It is evident therefore, that the Character of this Diſeaſe, is another degree, and manner of Diſtemper, ſuper-induced beſides that of their owne formerly introduced.</p>
               <p>And this conſideration alſo in of great moment; that in receiving this diſeaſe by Contact, (as in the next Chapter at large) this degree and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58193:21"/>manner of diſtemper, wherein it conſiſteth, is introduced after the manifeſt diſtemper is induced; yet ſo, as that there is no great ſpace of time, (rather a priority of nature then time,) between the degree im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and the diſtemper: which though at the beginning it may be disjunct from all proper matter, yet moſt commonly it is joyned to, and conveyed with, and in matter. And if not alwayes ſo, yet while it cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts the humours and ſpirits, bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els and members; it becomes the cauſe of begetting this corrupt and depraved matter, tough and viſcous <hi>ſanies,</hi> which is by degrees propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated in the humors and ſpirits, throughout all the bowels and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. And this is the manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing, and deriving the Venereous diſeaſe, which the next Chapter will more fully clear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:58193:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Cauſes of the Venereous Diſeaſe.</head>
               <p>NOw we ſhall enquire into the <hi>Cauſes,</hi> producing this Diſeaſe, which are either <hi>Externall,</hi> or <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</hi> The <hi>Externall</hi> are all compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under <hi>Contagion,</hi> and that is either <hi>Immediate,</hi> or <hi>Mediate.</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate contagion is, when there is an immediate Contact between the bodies infecting, and infected. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate, when ſome other body com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth between, which receiveth the infective vapour, and conveyeth it to the body, that is to be infected, (as the aire;) Either the common aire, or that portion of it, that by the infector is breathed out, and by the infected, is received in. Now that this diſeaſe cannot be contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58193:22"/>by the <hi>medium</hi> of common or outward air, is evident; for then, multitudes that dwell in places and neighbourhoods of venereous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, (as it falls out in times of peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent contagion) would daily be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, (eſpecially they that dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticaly cohabit, and kindreds moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, would be much endangered) which experience doth not confirm. So that this good hath the Venere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous plague beyond the other, that it keeps more at home, and doth not caſt forth ſo ſtrong a ſeminary of contagion, (though <hi>Fracastorus,</hi> an Author of no mean rank, thinketh otherwiſe.) Neither is it conveyed by aire, breathed out, and received in; for then, they that talk mouth to mouth with the Venereous, (and eſpecially ſuch as apply remedies to the ulcers of their mouth) muſt needs be infected; which is not found. It is true, the <hi>Tabes</hi> of the lungs communicateth a ſeminary of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58193:23"/>to the aire breathed out, ſo that they which are apt to receive that diſeaſe (drawing it in) are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered. But not for it ſelf, but as accompanied with an <hi>Hectick Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> But of this diſeaſe, it is not obſerved. So that, all mediate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tact being rejected, it followes, that onely by immediate and corporeall contact, this diſeaſe is conveyed. And hereby I underſtand, carnall uſe of a venereous perſon, ſucking venereous milk, or herditary diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition from the ſeed of venereous parents, (which <hi>Plautus in Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> calls <hi>Contagio.</hi>) The true man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then how this diſeaſe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, is no other but this, (as hath even now bin ſhewed) either by generation, lactation, or mutuall attrition of bodies; whereby defiled ſpirits (mixed with the pure) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate a degree and manner of diſtemper, together with a <hi>prava proluvies,</hi> (induced or produced)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58193:23"/>which running up and down the body, infecteth the bowells onely in ſome, and in others the members alſo; but in ſome, not, (being reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) as in Anſwer to the Queſtions ſhall be made appear.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Internall</hi> cauſe of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is no other, but, <hi>Ichor &amp; ſanies quaedam prava,</hi> (having their proper leaven in them) communicated, and tenaciouſly adhering to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and ſpirits. Why this <hi>Sanies</hi> is propagated, ſometimes, and in ſome, ſooner; in others, later; many cauſes may be alledged: 1. The la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude or ſtraitneſſe of the ſeminall paſſages; for, in wider pores and paſſages, this <hi>Illuvies</hi> is more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drunk in. Where the way is ſtrair, the diſeaſe doth ſeldomer, and more hardly propagate it ſelf. 2. A greater, or leſſe plenty of humours, as in bodies more or leſſe moiſt-3. Greater or leſſe diſpoſedneſſe of the bowells and members, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58193:24"/>or reſiſt the contagion. And hence is it, that they which have looſe fleſh, and abounding with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, (their veſſells being large and open-mouth'd) are ſooneſt tainted, (firſt, the humours; then, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitalls; next, the mouth) for theſe cauſes, and other reaſons before expreſſed.</p>
               <p>You may obſerve, that men of dryer, harder, and colder bodies, are leſſe ſubject to this diſeaſe, (as labouring men, poor men, old men). I have read it obſerved, that the Turks are not eaſily infected here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, though they have alwaies amongſt them venereous captives, of both ſexes; and the reaſon ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is, for that their bodies are more hard and drie, and conſequently their genitalls. And thus much for the cauſes, whereby you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, how this diſeaſe deriveth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuateth, and propagateth it ſelf. Now, (foraſmuch as no Argument
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58193:24"/>can be ſet forth ſo clearly, as to leave no darkneſſe or doubts in the mind of the Reader, eſpecially in this branch of it, touching the Cauſes.) I ſhall therefore farther endeavour his ſatisfaction, by ſolving ſuch Queſtions and Doubts, as may yet beclowd him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Doubts and Questions Reſolved, touching the Cauſes eſpecially.</head>
               <p n="1">1. QUeſt. <hi>Why may not Venereous contagion be conveyed medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately by the aire, (ſince we find aſſerted before, touching the</hi> Tabes <hi>of the lungs; and, by venerable Authors, of the</hi> Oph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalmia, <hi>that it ſends out ſpirits in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting the air; which the ſame air re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, (for a certain time and diſtance) communicateth by contagion to the eyes of others)? And if it be ſo in theſe caſes,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58193:25"/>why may not, from the ulcers in the mouths of the Venereous, infecting-va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours be ſent out into the aire, and that again infect others, as well as in the</hi> Opthalmia <hi>and</hi> Tabes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This diſeaſe lyeth prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily in the humours and naturall ſpirits, (for ſo I may call them) and they are more groſſe, and leſſe move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, &amp; cannot be emitted or darted out of the body, or, (if they ſhould) would take weak impreſſion upon the aire. The vitall ſpirits indeed are more ſubtile, and may paſſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and therefore diſeaſes, prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily in them, have a more flagrant ſeminary, to impoiſon the air. Yet, if this diſeaſe be accompanied with a feavour, (as, in time and grouth, it will) that may put ſtings into it, and render it mediately contagious.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>May not the contagion be conveyed by Garments, as ſome have thought?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No; for if the aire cannot
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58193:25"/>receive it, ſo as to convey it from perſon to perſon, much leſſe other externall bodies, which ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it from the air. For, qualities communicated to the aire, are alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and changed by further mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and change of fleeting aire; and ſo loſe their morbifick force.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>May not kiſſing the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, pledging them out of the ſame cup, ſitting next after them on the ſame ſtool, cloſe-stool; lying after them on the ſame bed, bed-cloaths, convey the infection?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The contrary hath been proved, that no mediate contact, can, of it ſelf, convey it; for, if the air or garments cannot, (for reaſons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed) much leſſe ſolider bodies, as cloſe-ſtools, and cups, leight con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tact of lips, &amp;c. And if they ſhould, then would this diſeaſe be much more ſpreading; and cohabitants with the Venereous, unavoidably be infected: ſo that Peſt-houſes were as neceſſary for theſe, as for the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous antiently, and of late for the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58193:26"/>viſited with the plague of Peſtilence. And although this diſeaſed (uſually) be a gentleman, yet common ſafety were preponderous to any man's private quality.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>May a woman bring this Diſeaſe upon her ſelfe, by proſtituting her body to many clean and uninfected men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To affirm this, doth ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe brothelry, debauched brothel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to be of late edition in the World; or at leaſt in thoſe places, or regions, where not withſtanding the Venere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Diſeaſe, never had a footing.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>May ſperm, oft injected by coition, with the ſame, or ſeverall clean Perſons, (clogging the expulſive faculty of the Womb) cauſe ſuch a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction, as that her Humors become venereouſly corrupted, and ſo the diſeaſe be produced?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, for if clean ſeed extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſate, by not being expelled the Womb, ſhould cauſe ſuch a putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, as to render the perſon Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nereous;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58193:26"/>then ſeed long detained and kept in the ſeminary veſſels, and there corrupting and putrifying, (the cauſe of the moſt leonine Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtericall fits, as is commonly aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) ſhould have much more cauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to produce this diſeaſe. But this cannot be granted, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not the former.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 6. <hi>What is the reaſon, that this Diſeaſe, which in ſome perſons, for ſome years lurketh in the body, ſo, as no ſigne of it appears; yet that at length, it ſhould diſcover it ſelfe, and break forth in great rage?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The venome of the biting of a mad Dog, lieth for ſome years in the body of ſome man, without any ſigne diſcovering it, (which all Phyſitians after <hi>Hippocra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) and yet neither he, nor any of the Ancients underſtood the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe; So may this <hi>Lues.</hi> But the manner How, and reaſon Why, is moſt worthy to come under Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. I ſaid before, that this <hi>prolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:58193:27"/>is viſcous, and therefore, tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly adheres to the bowels, and is mingled with the humors and ſpirits; but becauſe, evidence of its preſence cannot clearly, and by maniſeſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, be ſhewed but on ſolid bodies; which this venereous <hi>Illuvies</hi> doth find bowels ſo ſtrongly ſpirited, as that they make great reſiſtance, and refuſe it, and obtrude it into the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavities of the body, (where it lies fermenting) the diſeaſe reſideth eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in this Venereous <hi>Illuvies,</hi> and is not communicated to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards parts. So that, when, how, and where this diſeaſe begins, acts, and creeps on, is not perceived. There are workings and alterations, and morbifick ſenſations in the body, which are not (at all in ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, and in others not) percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by their proper cauſes, and are of tentimes attributed to other, than their owne. So that, if you put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the time, wherein the bowels reſiſt the Venereous poiſon, and the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58193:27"/>time wherein it worketh inſenſibly, together with the time of the bodies ſtate neutral; it may amount to a year, many years, before the effects, ſymptoms, and evidences, undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly diſcover the diſeaſe preſent.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 7. <hi>How comes it to paſſe, that ſometimes, and to ſome, at one coition with the Venereous, this diſeaſe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted; yet others can ſcarce be infected at many?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This muſt be aſcribed to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cauſes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To the various diſpoſitions of bodies; for ſome are more prone to this, or that diſeaſe, and therefore take it ſooner: for nature makes leſſe reſiſtance. Which alſo is the reaſon, that they which have any weak part of their bodies, do receive a diſeaſe ſooner in that part. For example, let a man that hath the gowt, be taken Venereouſly, and he ſhall find it more to prevaile, and afflict him in his feet. So on him that hath weak eyes, if this diſeaſe ſupervene; his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58193:28"/>eyes are ſooner, and more afflicted, than other parts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Careleſneſſe, ſordidneſs in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting their own bodies, is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe. For they that rightly and rationally cleanſe themſelves after coition, are ſcarcely, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domer, taken of this diſeaſe. But they that (having no care of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) do ſuffer the <hi>Illuvies</hi> to cleave unto them, are ſooner, and more fiercely, taken of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Long ſtay in carnall coition, makes much to infection; for they that welter in unclean bodies, (and, through the ecſtaſy of luſt, much inflame themſelves after ſaciety) are ſpeedily, and at one coition in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected: But they that ſoon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, and are leſſe inflamed, are not ſo eaſily ſtung.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They are ſooneſt infected that moſt burn in luſt, and are (with the horſe) more violently carried to coition, by a ſperm-fire. And hence it is, that ſo many of the younger
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58193:28"/>ſort are ſo ſoon infected. For when heat of youth, and heat of luſt, (more turgent, by ſpermatick and too liberall diet) meet together, there is a great flame, which makes them fearleſſe of a worſe, and greater. The like may be ſaid of them, <hi>qui rarò venere fruuntur;</hi> for when they obtain their deſires, they go on vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, and ſo are the ſooner infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. The reaſon is, becauſe a great conflux of ſtimulating ſpirits fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the genitalls, by whoſe heat and rage, the ſpermatick waies are much dilated, and ſo ſet the more open to the poyſon.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 8. <hi>Some move the Queſtion, Whether a woman, carnally known by a venereous man, and rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ining her ſelf (as to ſenſe, at least) uninfected; may yet infect him that next approacheth her?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Some hold the Negative, becauſe, <hi>Nemo dat quod non habet;</hi> and therefore it hardly finds credit, that a perſon uninfected, ſhould yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58193:29"/>another. But to hold the Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative, is to maintain that, which is neither impoſſible nor irrationall. It is evidenced already, that this <hi>Lues</hi> may lurk in the body many years, (in the humours and cavities) and therefore let it not ſeem ſtrange, if, in coition, it defile others. We have the ſtory in <hi>Avicen,</hi> of a young woman, nouriſhed up with poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous diet, who was never poyſoned her ſelf, and yet poiſoned all that had carnall uſe of her. You have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other preſident (in plague-times) of cats and dogs, who (not being infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted themſelves) carry the infection to others. So that the Affirmative is no abſurd aſſertion.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 9. <hi>whence comes it to paſſe, that at the beginning, when this diſeaſe came newly into</hi> Europe, <hi>it was ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midably raging; but now is became much more mild, and leſſe destructive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There were many cauſes conſpiring, that at firſt made this diſeaſe more fierce, which at this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58193:29"/>time ceaſing, (or abating their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity) it is reaſonable, the diſeaſe ſhould remit. The cauſes that made the diſeaſe ſo formidable at firſt, were, 1. Affrighting novelty, new and fierce ſymptoms, whereof they neither underſtood whence they aroſe, nor to what degree of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting they might aſcend. So that men being terrified by this novelty, and ignorant of the power of their enemy, became ſpirit-faln; and their bodies (not having the benefit of the counſell and courage of their minds) were delivered up captive to the diſeaſe, to do what it could on them. And this was one reaſon, why it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo formidable. For, as in times of Peſtilence, that diſeaſe affrights moſt at firſt; ſo, they are in moſt danger, which are moſt caſt down and trampled on by their own fears. Whereas the more careleſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident (having all the help, ſtrength, and defence, of courage and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the generous governing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58193:30"/>mind can give) are ſo much the more ſecure. So is it in this caſe. And this alſo is the reaſon, why the body, in ſleep, is more ſubject to the inclemency of the aire; for (not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing governed by the mind) it is wholly delivered up to the piercing aire, (it being of it ſelf able to make no reſiſtance) and therefore men are then moſt ſubject (as we phraſe it) to take cold, (which let them ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, who ſleep in their day-cloaths, without ſuperſtrate coverings.) 2. At the firſt breaking in of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, apt remedies were not found out, to arm men againſt the rage of it. The vertues of thoſe Indian-Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples (whence the diſeaſe came) were not known; and when they were found, it was looked upon as a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing dropt down from heaven, and the Inventors bleſſed. 3. When apt Simples were found, they were uſed (by moſt in practiſe) without weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reaſon; ſo that for want of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod to direct their uſe, thoſe reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58193:30"/>not onely proved fruitleſſe to ſome, but to others hurtfull. Bodies ill handled with acute medecines, become more defiled. 4. All enemies in their avaunt, ſhew themſelves moſt formidable. Time was, when the <hi>Yex,</hi> or <hi>Hicket,</hi> produced dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full effects; the Neezing (which we look upon as a remedy) was once a diſeaſe ſo deplorate, that by-ſtanders (terrified with it) brought in that cuſtom of praying over them, <hi>Chriſt help, &amp;c.</hi> which cuſtom prevailes to this day. So we read of the <hi>Mentagra</hi> and <hi>Gemurſa,</hi> diſeaſes, at their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, fierce, which afterwards became more remiſſe. And this leads me to the next Queſtion.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 10. <hi>What the reaſon ſhould be, that though this diſeaſe be generally milder, yet, on ſome, it appears very cruell?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hereof may be aſſigned ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons: 1. Either the diſeaſe finds weak bodies, full of corrupt humours, bodies paſſively diſpoſed;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58193:31"/>and hereby it becomes the more ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous. 2. Or the diſeaſe is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe, and finds nature yielding; and renued and ingeminated diſeaſes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver appear worſt. 3. Or other diſeaſes fallen in, are joyned with it, (one diſeaſe drawing on another his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate); and diſeaſes the more complicate, the worſe. 4. Beſides, the new diſeaſe falls in, when na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is weak, low, and languiſhing; ſo that its expulſive ability cannot keep out, or drive off the diſeaſes, new nor old.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 11. <hi>Whence comes it to paſſe, that this diſeaſe falls moſt, ſometimes on the hairs, ſometimes the nerves, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the bones, ſometimes the fleſhy parts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe they are more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and propenſe to receive it; or, becauſe they do leſſe repell it. Hence it is, that when and where the fleſh is weak, and doth leſſe reſiſt, (which ariſeth of many cauſes) then it falls on fleſhy or muſculous parts. And
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58193:31"/>the like may be ſaid of all the reſt. That which Phyſitians ſay of the Feavour-heat, (that ſometimes it falls on the humours, ſometimes on the ſpirits, and ſometimes on the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid parts, as they are more diſpoſed to inflammation, or do leſſe reſiſt that flame) may as truly be affirmed of this diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 12. <hi>Some move the queſtion, Whether there be any region or people, amongst whom this diſeaſe is more ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding? And the reaſon, why, they move, it, is, becauſe it is obſerved of old, that there are diſeaſes which have ſpread ſome Countries, for ſpeciall reaſons, and apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in the natives: as the</hi> Elephan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiaſis <hi>in</hi> Egypt, <hi>the gout in</hi> Attica, <hi>the</hi> Dracunculi <hi>in</hi> Arabia, <hi>the</hi> Aphthae <hi>in</hi> Syria. <hi>In</hi> Aethiopia, <hi>was a diſeaſe that ſent out of their bodies winged lice, and out of the ſame perforations grew a strange ſcab, which held them till death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To give reſolution to this queſtion, know; That all diſeaſes,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58193:32"/>(which diſtinctly befall ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries more than other) do ariſe; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from their diet, or from ſome evill conjunction of humors in, and thereby, inclinations of that people; or, from ſome winds, that bring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious vapours, by inſpiration aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulting them; or, from the temper of the aire, impreſſed by Influences. The ſcab of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> the <hi>Dracun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi</hi> of <hi>Arabia,</hi> (which the Ancients mention) came on them by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in diet; (for they were a vora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious people) and eſpecially, from their feeding on Locuſts, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved their conſtitutions. The gowt of <hi>Attica,</hi> aroſe from their full and delicious diet, and much venery. We read alſo of Winds, which brought the cauſes of ſickneſſes, (as the ſouth Wind from <hi>Africk</hi> to <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi>) and ſome Winds barrenneſſe to Women. So that all Endemicall diſeaſes, proper to regions ariſe; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from a corrupt uſage of thoſe Countries, or from the temper of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58193:32"/>aire. But this diſeaſe hath no ſuch riſe (adjuvant cauſes, I deny not) ſo that it cannot be peculiar to any region: but ſeeing it is gotten by contact, (eſpecially, that of coition) I ſay, it is moſt peculiar to thoſe Countries, Cities, Families, Perſons that are moſt addicted to Venery. And ſo I come from the Cauſes, and ſuch doubts as ariſe thereupon, unto the, Signes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the Signes, Diagnostick.</head>
               <p>THe ſignes of this diſeaſe, are either <hi>Diagnoſtick,</hi> or <hi>Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick: Diagnoſtick,</hi> or ſuch as diſcover the diſeaſe preſent, (beſides thoſe which have been ſcattered in the precedent Chapters) may from the accidentall differences of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, (the eſſence being alwayes the ſame) be rallied in this order: as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58193:33"/>they flow, 1. From the <hi>riſe,</hi> that one is <hi>haereditary</hi> and native, another <hi>accidentary;</hi> as by a ſoul bed, a vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reous Child to the Nurſe, or a vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reous Nurſe to the Child. 2. From the <hi>age</hi> of it; that one is <hi>begun,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>growing,</hi> a third <hi>conſummate.</hi> 3. From the <hi>ſymptoms;</hi> that one is more <hi>vehement,</hi> another <hi>milder,</hi> 4. From the <hi>ſex.</hi> 5. From the <hi>age of the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</hi> 6. From the <hi>conſtitution.</hi> 7. From the <hi>uſages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. From the <hi>riſe:</hi> for if the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance do not plainly ſpeak the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, (as by paint, it may be much ſilenced) yet it will give occaſion to enquire, whether they have not been carnally joyned to the venereous; whether they have not been infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or had reaſon to believe, that they deſcended of venereous parents, one or both; or had a venereous Nurſe; or ſhe a venereous Child. Theſe may make the matter proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and prevent, or ſtrengthen other enquiries. Otherwiſe, the ſignes
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58193:33"/>diſcovering, are not certain, and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but ſuſpitious, and conjecturall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Signes from the <hi>age</hi> of the diſeaſe, fall under three Heads; either as it is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Begun,</hi> for at entrance they are all obſcure, and general, and much common with other diſeaſes: as wearineſſe, (without labour) overthe whole body, moveable pains in the head and body, heavineſſe or ſloathfulneſſe of all inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of motion, unluſtfulneſſe after ſleep, the colour of the face changing, and growing darker. If it entred by a defiled bed; heat and ſharpneſſe of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, ſmart in the genitals, heat in the reins, dulneſſe, ſadneſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Growing on:</hi> virulent running of the reins, (green, yellow, or towards black) pains, ſwellings, ſoft tumors of of the privities, (one or all) with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing anguiſh. Sometimes a little feavour, (without any great ſignes of putrefaction) akeing of the perioſtia, or by the bone; pains increaſing in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, and later part of the night, and enraged by the heat of the bed; a little
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58193:34"/>cough, urine becomn ſabulous, pale, ſmelling ſtrong and rancid, ſpermaticall matter floating on it; ordure foeculent, of various forms and colours, (towards green, yellow, black) not onely in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, but in the ſame ſtool.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Conſummate and Confirmed,</hi> are, coldneſſe of nature, deſirous of the fire, a continued and ſetled pain of the head, in ſome part of it; tumors, ulcers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the head; flaccidity, looſneſſe of fleſh, and rottenneſſe of the privities; tumours, ulcers (or both) of the mouth, (which are ſometimes cruſty, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, purulent, ſometimes callous); whorſeneſſe of voice, ſpeaking through the palate or roof of the mouth, and noſe; not opening their mouths wide to ſpeak as formerly, and finding it pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſo to do; falling down of the noſe, and a ſtinking breath, from the carioſity thereof; falling of the hairs, eſpecially of the eye brows; ſometimes a painfull flying humour, from the brain, to the haemorhoid-veins, and thence a recur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the brain; hard knots in the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58193:34"/>legs, arms, neck, or all; rottenneſſe of the perioſtia and bones; tumours, and ſharp pains about the cheek-bones, ringing of the ears, clefts of the hands &amp; feet; and grievous tormenting pains throughout the whole body; which becommeth emaciate, (appetite being decayed, and concoction much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned); dimneſſe of ſight, the colour of the eyes changed, (having loſt their bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and agility) become ſlow of motion; ſtinking, loathſome, ſlimy ſweats; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phous knots, (like thoſe of the gout) the colour of the skin becomming ſtill more darkſome, ſquallid, and like the countenance in a black Jaundies; Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boes ſwelling out in the <hi>Inguina,</hi> and ſometimes falling in, (flying from place to place, eſpecially of the Emun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories). Moſt commonly it appears in this order. Firſt, by acrimony, and ſharpneſſe of urine, virulent running of the reins, (and ſometimes not, which is ſeldom.) This flowing, women oft mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake for the Whites, whereby the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is let grow on unperceived. Then,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58193:35"/>puſtules appear, (ariſing firſt about the genitalls;) next, ſwelling gums, knots. Thence cruſty ſores, white in the midſt, and red round about, which being bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken give caſe.) Then pains of the Head, in the evening increaſing. After that, buboes about the <hi>Inguina,</hi> growing as big as Eggs. Then Tophous knots. At length, Ulcers of the Noſe, palate, and cruell pains.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Signes from the <hi>ſymptoms;</hi> which ever at beginning are milder, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards more fierce. This is the reaſon, why the patient neglects the beſt ſeaſon of Cure, governing the care of his health, by ſenſe of pain; which (creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on inſenſibly) makes him think the diſtemper will ſpend it ſelf, and ſo wear away.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Signes from the <hi>ſex;</hi> for the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker ſex have ſome benefit above the ſtronger, (to abate the diſeaſe by Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and monthly clenſings) but a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter miſchief, by the paſſive and recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive formation of their bodies, (lodging virulent ſperme) and (being of more
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58193:35"/>ſoft and ſpungy bodies) are more apt to receive contagion, and have weaker hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, and ſpirits to reſiſt, and repell the ſame. And hence it is, that the ſignes and ſymptoms, before mentioned on them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, do become more fierce and dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Signes from the <hi>age of the Patient:</hi> As more years are an advantage againſt infection, (old men do not ſo eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, and the ſignes and ſymptoms do not appear ſo fierce) ſo have they thereby a greater diſadvantage, for if they are once ſeized, it ſeldome departs but with Life.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Signes from the <hi>conſtitution,</hi> and temperament. The Cholerick are ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt tanged, the Melancholly moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, the ſanguine make beſt reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to infection, and are beſt Cured; the Phlegmatick have it lying longeſt in their humors, (all which muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into Conſideration, when you exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine upon the ſigns before mentioned.)</p>
               <p>Laſtly, From the <hi>Uſages.</hi> The tender and idle take it ſooneſt, are moſt afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58193:36"/>and with greateſt difficulty Cured: Contrarily, laborious and dry bodies. And thus you have a Catalogue of the ſignes, (not all, for that were endleſſe): about which, three things are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That all theſe, at the entrance of the diſeaſe are leſſe viſible, and more mild; but as the diſeaſe growes on, do more appear and rage.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That as it is not neceſſary, that all theſe ſignes concurr where ever the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is; ſo it is hard to find a venere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous body, on which one of theſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears alone, (for if there befalling of the hairs, there are alſo Ulcers, Tumors, and manifold Pains; and ſo of all the reſt.) For you ſhall never find one la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring under this diſeaſe (growen) but many of theſe ſignes conſpire to blab, and diſcover it; and the reaſon is, (becauſe the <hi>fomes</hi> of this diſeaſe is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the humors, (as is before ſaid) which are diſperſed throughout the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, from which each bowell and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber with its nouriſhment, having its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filement)
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58193:36"/>filement) ſo that it cannot be, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe ſhould have but one window to look out at.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That moſt of theſe ſigns are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by other diſeaſes; yet, in two things they differ: One is, The contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy or ſtubbornneſſe of this diſeaſe, and its accidents, beyond thoſe of other diſeaſes. The other is, The diſobedience and oppoſition, that this diſeaſe makes to all ordinary remedies. When you find a diſeaſe (ſeeming another) throughout not obedient to the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, left us by the Antients, you may vehemently ſuſpect to be Venereous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the Signes Prognoſtick, or diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Event of this Diſeaſe.</head>
               <p>THis diſeaſe of it ſelf is ſeldom and ſlowly mortall. I ſay, Of it ſelf; for it may, and oft doth, beget, or is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with another, more nimbly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58193:37"/>mortall, (for diſeaſes ſeldom go alone.) Unleſſe it fall on a flaming conſtitution. It is no acute, but chronick diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and therefore worſt in old men. (<hi>Hippocrates</hi> gives the reaſon, 2 <hi>Aph. Old men are leſſe ſubject to ſickneſſe than the younger; but their diſeaſes are wont to be long, and accompany them till death.</hi>) Again, This diſeaſe contracted by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition onely, is eaſieſt cured; next, when brought on by the breſt; and hardeſt, when inherited. Beſides, they that purge well by childbed, termes, or flowing haemorrhoides, are leſſe ſubject to, or afflicted by this diſeaſe; and on them it is more eaſily cured, (they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many ordinary Sewers for corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.) Likewiſe, if there be a falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of hairs, a proneneſſe to ſweat, the diſeaſe is the ſafer; (for when it falls outward, and the skin open) it appears the ſooner to be removed; but the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the diſeaſe lodgeth, the harder the cure. Alſo, if the diſeaſe be joyned with a feaver, the more conſiderable the feavour, the harder the cure. For the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58193:37"/>remedies which remove the venereous diſeaſe, (being hot and dry) encreaſe the feaver. Laſtly, diſeaſes, by relapſe, the oftner, the worſe. For, if rationall means could not remove the bodie's diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to this diſeaſe, it becommeth ſtill more prone and ſuccumbent to it; therefore in ſuch caſes, the patient needs a more prudent and well-furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Artiſt. And ſo much for the ſignes. Before I enter upon the Cure, it will be neceſſary to remove ſome doubts, which tend to the clearing of what hath been delivered, and make way to the Cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Doubts and Queſtions Reſolved.</head>
               <p n="1">1. QUeſt. <hi>Why doth this diſeaſe (which hath ſuch cruell ſymptoms, and ſometimes ſuch as are commenſurate with life it ſelf) ordinarily kill ſo ſlowly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Death comes not, but when the heart is vehemently injured; and Nature ever (what it can) preſerves
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58193:38"/>and defends that fortreſſe, eſpecially againſt this diſeaſe. Beſides, this diſeaſe of it ſelf begets no feaver, but by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. In this diſeaſe, Reſpiration is not changed, but rarely, and at laſt extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. The Pulſe is not altered, for there are no diagnoſtick ſignes from thence of this diſeaſe, (a good evidence, that Nature defends the Heart.) But, <hi>de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do quaeritur,</hi> which take thus. The vital ſpirits are the moſt mighty inſtruments of Nature, to ſecure themſelves and her. Their fire is ever in oppoſition to, and depuration of, and from, what is heterogenious, (and, againſt what is moſt oppoſite, moſt active.) And the oftner they paſſe the elaboration of the heart, the more ſtrong they become. That which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith of Choler, (how truly, I do not affirm) <hi>Quarto de part. Animal. [That the heart will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer choler to come near it, becauſe choler is a great enemy to the heart]</hi> the like do I ſay of this venereous poiſon, The heart will not ſuffer it to come near it, but ever, by the vital ſpirits, oppugns it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58193:38"/>it is a great enemy unto it; and the heat of the heart is ever in depuration of them. As impure gold is (by the fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heat, and ſeparating ability) illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, purified, perfected; ſo, the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and ſpirits (venereouſly defiled) by the hearts heat, are purified and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, the leſſe and more ſlowly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>Whether this diſeaſe be cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? Whether it be true, (which ſome affirm) that it never makes peace, but truce onely?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Experience evidenceth the contrary. It is true, that unleſſe this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe be ſeaſonably ſet on, and reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it takes deeper roots; and though at beginning it hath ſecret and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground workings, and do leſſe, or not at all appear, (for reaſons formerly ſhewed) yet, with time, it takes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and diſcovereth it ſelf. Now, one reaſon why this diſeaſe is ſo ſeldom cured, ariſeth from the Patient, who being (by the induſtry of the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) once delivered from fierce ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms, and ſenſe of pain, too haſtily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58193:39"/>confident of being cured; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines obedience to further indeavours: ſo that the diſeaſe-ſtill lurks in the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, (and with them imbibed by the bowels and members) and breaks forth again. Hence hath riſen that proverbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſpeech, that it admits a truce, not a peace.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>Whether, as time was, when this diſeaſe was not, (for it is a ſtranger un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, not endemicall) ſo time ſhall be, when it ſhall ceaſe? Whether it ſhall have but a ſeaſon onely; as the</hi> Mentagra, <hi>and</hi> Gemur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa <hi>in</hi> Italy, <hi>and the</hi> Sweating ſickneſs <hi>in</hi> England?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is propable that it ſhall be ſo, and this I am induced to think from theſe conjectures. 1, Becauſe, other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes formerly not known, (nor being) had but their ſeaſons, and now are anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quated and extinct, (as is inſtanced in the queſtion.) 2, Becauſe, ſince this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe began in <hi>Europe,</hi> it is much abated of its rage: and that which may abate, may aboliſh. If you ask me, how this ſhould come to paſſe? I anſwer, many
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58193:39"/>wayes, 1. By diet, and manner of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, men will become more choiſe and frugall, 2. They have, and will learn more prudence in coition; and as time teacheth men diſcretion, ſo will they more avoid this contagion, 3. Cleanli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe about the body, will do much to effect this, (as in anſwer to the ſeventh queſtion.) I ſhall further give probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to this opinion, by anſwer to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Queſtion, thus. Why was the plague of Peſtilence, and Leproſie ſo frequent formerly, and now ſo rare? (Or, if the Peſtilence break forth, is oft ſo ſoon quelled?) No reaſon, (as to men) can be given, but, that men have more care of their diet, skill to manage preſervatives, are more diligent in clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Cities, and Habitations, have more care of their perſons in avoiding contagion: The ſame may be ſaid of this diſeaſe. It raged formerly, becauſe men were more negligent of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: but time and experience teach them more prudence.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>Doth not the ſupervention of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58193:40"/>this diſeaſe, cure and remove the falling-ſickneſſe, Aſthma, or other mortall diſeaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I know, it is affirmed by ſome, and they give this reaſon; becauſe, by this diſeaſe, there is a totall change wrought upon nature: ſo that it ſhould eaſily come to paſſe, that thoſe almoſt naturall diſeaſes (mentioned) ſhould hereby be removed. But theſe are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacies; for, grant that by this diſeaſe, a great change is made on nature; yet it is a change to the worſe. Therefore, how can it be, that thoſe diſeaſes, which (in a body otherwiſe ſound) are of themſelves difficult, ſhould (being coupled with a more depraved diſeaſe) become more eaſily cured?</p>
               <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>Doth the Pox keep out the Plague?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I know it hath been vulgarly aſſerted, that the venereous are ſecure againſt Peſtilent contagion: and they give this reaſon, becauſe another kind of diſtemper prevaileth in the venere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, diſtinct from that which is apt to produce peſtilent diſeaſes. They argue
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58193:40"/>alſo from experience, that venereous houſes and perſons, are ſeldom viſited with peſtilent diſeaſes. But theſe are trifles; for the character of the peſtilence is Putrefaction, (whether occult or not) venenous putrefaction. And who can deny putrefaction in this diſeaſe? and that the humours, ſpirits, bowels, and members, (depraved by it) are apt further to beget it? So that it cannot be hoped, that one kind of putrefaction ſhould ſecure againſt another. Onely thus far it is true, that (if any venere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon hath been lately and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured) he is the leſſe ſubject to peſtilent infection; and the reaſon is, becauſe the <hi>Fomes</hi> of putrefaction is taken away in the venereous cure. But, that one plague keeps out another, is a pleaſant dream, and were a madneſſe to affirm.</p>
               <p>Queſt. 6. <hi>Whether there be any Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote, any true and certain means of avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contagion; ſo as, that a man may uſe a venereous woman, and yet not be infected by her?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:58193:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I know there are thoſe, who promiſe great matters this way; and (that they may feed their own cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, and others luſt, and factor for the devill) do boaſt of their ſecrets in this kind, as if they were skild beyond others, to give an Antidote, that ſhould ſecure againſt ſuch venereous contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But I look upon theſe pleaſant and wicked fales, as cheats, and methods of baſe gain. For we know, that in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition, there is a mutuall attrition of genitals, a mixture of humours and ſpirits; (for the pores, by ſuch flames, are ſet open) ſo that it cannot be, but that infected ſpirits ſhould be mixed with the pure, in thoſe pores, and they ſo become defiled. 'Tis true, ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylactick medecines may do two things: 1. They may, <hi>denſare poros ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitalium,</hi> ſo that the paſſages of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and ſpirits may be leſſe patent. 2. They may corroborate and confirm the ſpirits, that they may the more ſtrongly repell the infection, (as Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles do againſt poyſon.) But there is a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58193:41"/>different reaſon between poiſons that are taken inwardly, and this diſeaſe, which is contracted by Contact; for poiſons do not alwaies and preſently mingle themſelves, with the humors and ſpirits, as this doth. Beſides, poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons firſt enter the ſtomack, (which preſently repells them, as appeareth in dogs vomitings) then are diſperſed through the veſſells, and contaminate the ſpirirs: but this Peſt preſently enters the inward parts, by defiling the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and ſpirits. Laſtly, ſuch things as preſerve from poiſon, are taken inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they may be diffuſed throughout the whole body, and ſo confirm the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and bowels. But the medecines (to which theſe attribute ſo great vertue) are outward things, which cannot dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe their efficacy through the inward parts. Again, if there be any medecines to be given, which ſhall preſerve from this infection, it muſt be thoſe Antidotes which cure the diſeaſe, (as Treacles cure the poiſoned, they alſo preſerve from poiſon.) But the Indian Woods,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58193:42"/>which (though more flowly) do at length cure this diſeaſe, cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, but that they which uſe them, may at the ſame time be infected; much leſs can other remedies. But you will object, that many go in to the Venre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and yet find, by experience, that they are not infected (which yet is more than they can be aſſured of:) And then; that which Nature doth for ſome, Why may not Art do for others? I anſwer, Art cannot impreſſe upon the ſpirits ſuch a faculty of refiſting, as Nature can. Yet, I do not deny, but that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes may be found, which may work, <hi>in tantum,</hi> that men may not ſo eaſily be taken of this diſeaſe; but, that they may promiſe them ſafety, I utterly deny. Therefore let none ſuffer themſelves to be deluded; for, to avoid this danger, they have onely theſe three remedies: To maintain Chaſtity, To live Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, and, To avoid the Venereous.</p>
               <p>Queſtt. 7. <hi>Is the venereous cure to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, as ſoon as the diſeaſe, by any ſigne or just ſuſpition, diſcovereth it ſelf?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:58193:42"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I know, ſome are for the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, and they tell us of their experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, That they have found the diſeaſe thereby exaſperated. Alſo they argue further, that the diſeaſe may be cured and expelled at firſt by Nature it ſelf; but (when provoked by Medecines) it further ſpreads throughout the body. But this opinion is not more falſe than pernicious; for, all men reſt in that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule, <hi>Principiis obsta;</hi> and (from <hi>Hippoc. de locis in hom. &amp; de ſacro morbo</hi>) that a diſeaſe muſt be withſtood at the beginning; and that great care is to be uſed, that young diſeaſes be forthwith extinguiſhed. Now, as this is a good rule in the curing of all diſeaſes, ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of this; for at firſt, this diſeaſe (when taken by impure coition) lodgeth in the out-parts, and needs not medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines that work by alteration, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion. And who doubts of the truth of that, <hi>Turpiùs ejicitur, &amp;c?</hi> that venom is more eaſily driven out of the porch, than turned out of the houſe; when it enters by the genitalls, than when it
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58193:43"/>hath taken its walk through the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and bowels? And ſo I come to the cure in the next Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of the Cure in Common.</head>
               <p>THe Cure hath two branches, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as <hi>common</hi> to other diſeaſes, in the uſe of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niv rſals;</hi> or, as <hi>Speciall</hi> and proper to this, <hi>Antivenereal.</hi> And this again; either the cure of the diſeaſe it ſeif, or of the ſymptoms, which are many and fierce. And though ſome go off, or abate, with the diſeaſe; yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers require ſpeciall cure, (which is done by Chirurgicall applications, whereof I need not further trouble the Reader.) Now the cure in common, conſiſts in the right uſe of <hi>Catharicks, Phlebotomy, Diaphoreticks;</hi> for if this Peſt be to be thrown out, all paſſages are to be ſet open, that way may be made for the ſpeciall cure. A method is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58193:43"/>from this diſtemper, and all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, (for it rarely goes alone) and all other indications. The fix things cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not-naturall, muſt be rightly orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Venery, for a ſeaſon, baniſhed, that ſo the <hi>Vires</hi> may be kept ſtrong, to expell a diſeaſe of long cure, and ſhort diet; and leſt, by inflaming-motion of the body in coition, the diſeaſe entred in one part be diffuſed. Phlebotomy is (in caſe of Plethory, or fierce accidents) to be uſed, and not (as is the manner of ſome) in all venereous cures, to breathe a vein preſently. Diaphoreticks in growen diſeaſes are of great moment, and require due management.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the Cure in Speciall.</head>
               <p>AS there are many methods of <hi>Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> Cures, ſo they may all be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to theſe two heads, <hi>Reproved,</hi> or <hi>Approved.</hi> Methods <hi>Reproved</hi> are,</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:58193:44"/>
               <p n="1">1. By remedies common, and not Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificall, which find no obedience here; or, not without a greater miſchief, than benefit to Nature.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The good cheap poor whore cure, by <hi>Fontanels,</hi> taken up from the practice of the poorer Spaniards, (amongſt whom it is in common uſe) whereby Nature findeth ſome eaſe, (disburthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning part of the purulent matter), but the <hi>fomes</hi> is left within, to render their condition deplorate. I am no friend to continued Iſſues, which prevailed not in practiſe, untill this diſeaſe brake in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. By <hi>Mercuriall Unguent,</hi> which may ſerve for Carriers and Porters, ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtious bodies; and yet, even in them, the conſequents render it perilous, if not pernitious. I know, ſome are ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and audacious, that they make it their ordinary Champion, ſetting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every venereous patient with this dreadfull remedy, as if no cure could be diſpatched without it; the effects of whoſe boldneſſe, many have mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58193:44"/>carried to their graves. What this Unguent is, I need not expreſſe; its compoſition is well known, better than truſted to, or delighted in by Artiſts. For, this Unguent, rubb'd on the palms and plants of hands and feet, is ſpeedily carried to the head, (as appears by the floods of ſalivation that follow the uſe of it.) For its Mercury (being an aerial &amp; ſpirituous body compacted as appeareth by its orbicular &amp; trembling motion) as ſoon as it is attenuated, and reſolved by naturall heat, breaks out of its compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, as fired powder out of a gun, and (naturally flying upwards) is carried through veins and arteries to the brain, with many vapours accompanying it; which Vapours and Mercury (there condenſing) are attenuated, eliquated, as a cloud for rain; and, through the palate are caſt down to the mouth or ſtomack, in ſalivation. The truth of this appears to them, (who, in ſalivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hold a piece of gold in their mouthes) who find the ſpirits and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours of the Mercury (concreating)
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58193:45"/>hang about it; as it doth about other ſolid bodies: for its ſubtile flying ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits paſſe through the whole body, and fix about the bones alſo, who receive on themſelves the ſubſtance and colour of the Mercury, (as in the mouth about the gold.)</p>
               <p n="4">4. By Mercuriall Cinnaber-fume, which is yet more formidable; and (to ſuch as have pectorall diſeaſes, ſhort breath, ill affected lungs, are troubled with diſtillations, weak bowells, chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick pains, dyſenteries) pernicious; uſe what care you can, Mercuriall aire will get in. There being ſafe methods of cure, let theſe be laid aſide: for ſcarce to any perſon are they uſed, without the manifeſt offence and detriment of ſome bowell. And though great pretenders may promiſe ſecurity in its uſe, yet it is no wiſdome to adventure your perſon upon every one's, bold raſh, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant confidence; <hi>Melius est non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe, quàm obeſſe,</hi> Fierce accidents will all in. Bold Empericks will promiſe much, and perform little; and will
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58193:45"/>adventure upon what they cannot go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern: and therefore muſt needs abuſe themſelves, and their <hi>patients.</hi> I do not decry the right uſe of Mercury; for, take away Mercury, Antimony, and Vitriol, you leave the Armory of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, reproachfully weak.</p>
               <p>The Methods of cure <hi>approved,</hi> are</p>
               <p n="1">1. That by <hi>Treacles</hi> and <hi>Indian Alexipharmaca,</hi> which in time, and right uſe, will take effect: but this way is long and tedious.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That by <hi>Antivenereall Magnets;</hi> which is noble, and to be reſted in; ſure, potent, and effectuall to draw out the venereous matter: which let none deſpiſe, becauſe they do not underſtand by ſuch hints. <hi>Dii laboribus omnia vendunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Laſt is, that by <hi>Sympatheticall</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication; which ſaveth the patients much trouble, and uſeth nature in her moſt ſublime, and nobleſt activities. (Theſe two laſt Methods of cure, let the weaker ſex eſpecially take notice of whoſe more tender bodies, and feeble ſpirits, render them more unable to bea
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58193:46"/>the more rough and difficult wayes of cure.) Theſe are methods, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men, of great attainments otherwiſe, (through pride and unthankfullneſſe) have rendred themſelves uncapable of. What the Magneticks are, how applied, and by what cauſality they operate; what the Sympatheticks to be choſen are, and by what ſymmetry, oneneſs, and community of ſpirit, they have their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or whereby their cauſality is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, or ſet on motion, <hi>longa dies docuit;</hi> every one is not fit to receive it, nor would underſtand if they were told, nor could apply if they underſtood. The learned unprejudiced, may inform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. If any one find a new <hi>ſpring</hi> iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> reaſon will, that he firſt drink the waters thereof. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect will beſt commend the work, and the patients <hi>Euge's</hi> the cure: and that's enough to ſecure againſt the mad tooth of detraction, and ſilence the charge of Novelty, (the ſtrength whereof others, (famous in their generation) have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to my hands.) For who knowes
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58193:46"/>not, that the opinion of the Circulation of the blood is new, and thereupon the doctrine of Feavers fundamentally new, the way of the Chyle new, the ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the heart, veins, maſſe of blood it ſelfe new, the proper work of the Liver new, the Chymicall anatomy of all mixt bodies new, the whole frame and face of naturall Philoſophy new: and yet the Aſſertors of theſe not deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by any, but proud Stoicks, whom no reaſon can perſwade that they are men. Phyſick came in at firſt Empiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, (though it ſtood not ſo) and by induction of manifold experience it was brought into Precepts and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: And had the way of improving experience, been longer ſtood on, and Phyſick too ſoon not taught to ſyſtema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize it had better improved, and fewer breaches been made on its doctrine; to the greater honour of the Art, and its Profeſſors, and benefit of Patients. But this practicall Art muſt be like ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Sciences, and take a body of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Principles before they be found <hi>ſide
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58193:47"/>digna,</hi> &amp; ſufficient cauſes of Concluſion. But had they been ſuch; the Fabrick had been firmer. It is true, and cannot be denyed, that naked Experience, (not ſupported by weighty Reaſon) is but a dwarf, and can do little; nay, is often miſchievous: but they that joyne both together, will find them a fortreſſe ſtrong enough to abide the battery of calumny. If (in theſe methods of cure) I walk in paths leſſe trodden, yet (ſince my foundation is pureſt Philoſophy) I ſhall ſay for my ſelfe, <hi>Salve amicum lumen!</hi> I will not, with ſome others, <hi>contra rationem inſanire.</hi> All the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, I ſhall in concluſion give the Reader, (and that will ſatisfie the ſober and modeſt) is, to remit him to that of <hi>Seueca.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Multi ad ſapientiam pervenire potuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent niſi putaſſent ſe perveniſſe — Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum egerunt qui ante nos fuerunt, ſed non peregerunt. Multum adhuc restat operae, multumque restabit; neque ulli nato poſt mille ſecula praecidetur occaſio aliquid adhuc adjiciendi.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:58193:47"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap I.</hi> THE Preface. <hi>Pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap II.</hi> The Names. <hi>Pag. 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap III.</hi> The Definition. <hi>Pag. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap IV.</hi> The Subject. <hi>Pag. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap V.</hi> The Affect it ſelf. <hi>Pag. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap VI.</hi> The Cauſes. <hi>Pag. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap VII.</hi> Doubts and Queſtions reſolved touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cauſes, <hi>viz. Pag. 31</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Whether the diſeaſe may be conveyed by the air? <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Whether by garments? <hi>Pag. 32</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Whether by drinking after the Venereous of the ſame cup, ſitting after on the ſame ſtool, lying next af er on the ſame bed? <hi>Pag. 33</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Whether a woman, by much proſtitution to clean men, may contract it? <hi>Pag. 34</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> Whether by extinguiſhing the expulſive faculty of the womb? <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> Why the diſeaſe oft lurks in the body, &amp;c? <hi>Pag. 35</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> Whence it is, that ſome are infected ſooner than others? <hi>Pag. 37</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58193:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8.</hi> Whether a woman, having coition with a venereous man, may remain uninfected, and yet ſhe infect others? <hi>Pag. 39</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9.</hi> Whence it is, that this diſeaſe at firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entrance into <hi>Europe,</hi> was ſo formidable, but now is more milde? <hi>Pag. 40</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>10</hi> Whence it is, that though the diſeaſe be generally milder, yet it is cruel on ſome? <hi>Pag. 43</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>11.</hi> Why the diſeaſe falls moſtly, in ſome, on the Hairs; in others, on the Nerves, Bones, &amp;c? <hi>Pag. 44</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>12.</hi> Whether this diſeaſe be proper to any Country, and to what, &amp;c? <hi>Pag. 45</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap VIII.</hi> The Signes Diagnostick. <hi>Pag. 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap IX.</hi> The ſignes Prognoſtick. <hi>Pag. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap X.</hi> Queſtions leading to the cure, <hi>viz. Pag. 57</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Why this diſeaſe kills ſo ſlowly? <hi>ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Whether this diſeaſe be curable? <hi>Pag. 59</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Whether (as time was, when the diſeaſe was not) it will in time ceaſe to be? <hi>Pag. 60</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Whether the ſupervention of this diſeaſe doth cure the Falling-ſickneſſe, &amp;c. or other mortall diſeaſes? <hi>Pag. 61</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> Whether the Pox keep out the Plague? <hi>Pag. 62</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58193:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> Whether there be any Antidote to keep a man (uſing a venereous wonan) from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infected? <hi>Pag. 63</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> Whether Cure be to be endeavoured at firſt entrance of the diſeaſe? <hi>Pag. 66</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XI.</hi> Of the Cure in Common. <hi>Pag. 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. XII.</hi> Of the Cure in Speciall. <hi>Pag. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Some Methods Approved, others Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved. <hi>Pag. 70</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
